<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>BIBBOX</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/</link><description>Recent content on BIBBOX</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 13:31:45 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://webtest.bibbox.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Common Apps</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/apps/common-apps/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 13:31:45 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/apps/common-apps/</guid><description>A list of the most used BIBBOX Apps with description and category can be found below:
App Description Category GitHub OpenSpecimen OpenSpecimen is a biobank/biospecimen management tool. Biobank https://github.com/bibbox/app-openspecimen-fair MOLGENIS MOLGENIS is a web-based application for management and analysis of scientific data. Data management https://github.com/bibbox/app-molgenis-fair PhenoTips PhenoTips is a web-based tool for medical genetics, recording linked clinical phenotype, genetic, disease, and family history data for patients with genetic diseases. Biobank https://github.</description></item><item><title>Playground &amp; Demo</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/demo/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 11:14:40 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/demo/</guid><description>To give an impression of the BIBBOX, we provide a playground and a demo instance.
BIBBOX Playground The website www.demo.bibbox.org is a playground that allows users to experiment with the functionalities of the BIBBOX. This playground is an example of the BIBBOX, which can be used to test BIBBOX Apps.
Note that this is a public instance, everyone can access it, see the data and change it.
The Apps&amp;rsquo; instances will only be available for a short time and will be reset after a week.</description></item><item><title>FAIRified Apps</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/apps/app-examples/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 10:56:58 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/apps/app-examples/</guid><description>FAIRified Apps are BIBBOX Apps that were extended with a FAIR Data Point. We extended three Apps with a FAIR Data Point: Molgenis, OpenSpecimen, and PhenoTips. We deliberately chose Apps that are used in various scientific disciplines. Users can use demo data to test these three Apps. We provide a user management system and several demo users with different permission rights, in order to demonstrate roles such as admin, biobank user, and researcher.</description></item><item><title>Architecture</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/about/architecture/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 10:23:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/about/architecture/</guid><description>The BIBBOX runs on Linux, and its core architecture strongly relies on the use of Docker. In the BIBBOX framework, the software tools are encapsulated into Docker Containers and BIBBOX Apps are simply a group of Docker Containers, ready to be used. Therefore, they can run quickly and reliably in any computing environment.
The main components of the BIBBOX are the BIBBOX Portal, the Master FAIR Data Point, and the Apps.</description></item><item><title>Create your own BIBBOX App</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/apps/create-app/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 10:23:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/apps/create-app/</guid><description>Creating a BIBBOX App Starting with an existing open-source software solution that handles data, one can easily transform it into a BIBBOX App, following the tutorial at https://bibbox.readthedocs.io/en/latest/.
Each BIBBOX App must be published in the BIBBOX GitHub repository, by creating a repository named app-nameofapp. The repository app-template aims to guide users when creating an App.
Briefly, the most important components of a BIBBOX App are: The Base Docker is a container created from a Docker Image of the existing software tool.</description></item><item><title>Fair</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/about/fair/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 10:23:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/about/fair/</guid><description>What is FAIR? European guidelines recommend that scientific data should be made FAIR: findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable [1]. However, FAIR guidelines do not specify how the stated principles should be implemented, it might not be straightforward for researchers to know how to actually make their data FAIR.
The BIBBOX allows researchers to publish their data and the associated data management software (Apps) in a FAIR manner, through the incorporation of a FAIR Data Point into the Apps.</description></item><item><title>Get Started</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/get-started/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 10:23:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/get-started/</guid><description>The installation of the BIBBOX software needs 3 essential steps or requirements:
an available server that is based on Linux by default the installation of Docker on this server the installation of the BIBBOX software on this server To provide your own server, we recommend to contact your respective IT department. Instead of the server mentioned, a virtual machine can also be set up on a normal computer, which can take over the tasks of a server.</description></item><item><title>Project</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/about/project/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 10:23:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/about/project/</guid><description>Motivation Biological resources, such as cells, tissues or biomolecules are considered as the essential raw material for the advancement of biotechnology, human health, and for research and development in life sciences.
Scientific research went through significant changes, expanding from single projects, using few data processing tools, to transnational consortia, working with a wide range of commercial and open-source software packages. These changes demand a high level of research collaboration and availability of software tools.</description></item><item><title>Provenance</title><link>http://webtest.bibbox.org/about/provenance/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 10:23:24 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://webtest.bibbox.org/about/provenance/</guid><description>What is Provenance: You can look at provenance as the history of a data object, for example how a sample has been created and where it has been stored.
Provenance, as defined in the ISO Provenance Standard ISO 23494 - “Biotechnology – Provenance information model for biological specimen and data – Part 2: Common Provenance Model” is expressed as a triplet of &amp;ldquo;Entity - Agent - Activity&amp;rdquo;. The entity was generated by an activity, which has been performed by an agent.</description></item></channel></rss>